Hello and welcome. Today we will be
looking at something new about
subcontracting.
It's not technically very very new
because we are silently released it in
minor update three, but in this time we
did not pre-install it on new
environments, neither on upgraded ones.
So, up was available on App Store,
available for installation, but not
forced. We gathered feedback and now
we are kind of reintroducing it in a
different level.
All right. What are we will be talking
today about?
Definitely demonstrations of the whole
flow because original subcontracting
which was present in Business Central
for many years was
maybe
a little bit limited.
It allowed you to register fact that
subcontracting happened and buy the
stuff, but a lot of components
were added only recently.
So, and in this
session we will have a lot of demos
focusing about different subcontracting
capabilities.
Starting with a logistics of raw
materials, but also with logistic of
working product progress items. There's
something which
kind [clears throat] of assembled, but
not yet, but you would like still to
track how it was moved to and back from
subcontractor.
And uh
also we have a dramatically better
integration with powerful warehouse
handling which we have in the standard
Business Central available for the
wholesale operations and manufacturing.
Now subcontracting operations can
benefit from the same warehouse uh
processes. So, no need to
handle them differently.
And we have two
important nuances. We also adding more
powerful price management, as well as a
extra ability to allocate cost.
Why? We will look at this later during
the demos.
But before we will start,
how can you get it?
As I mentioned, for new environments in
the latest version, you will get up
pre-installed. But if you are upgrading
from the previous versions, you have
several options. Option number one,
navigate to Microsoft Marketplace and
find Subcontracting up there and install
it.
If you for
very good reasons do not want to leave
your Business Central environment, you
can do the same right from the product.
You navigate to Microsoft AppSource list
there and find Subcontracting up and
install it from here.
If you feel that searching for and
selecting among many Microsoft apps is a
difficult task, we have a even easier
way.
Just open
the Subcontracting worksheet, the
existing one,
and you will get notification
that Subcontracting up will be replacing
this legacy Subcontracting worksheet,
and you can actually install
Subcontracting up right from here. Just
click install and install extension.
I will not do it here because I have
another environment ready.
Once ready, you will see Subcontracting
assisted setup, which is actually
allows you to populate some default
values, but we are filling in them
automatically.
If you want, you can change something.
And giving the links to uh other places
related to Subcontracting.
Let's explore them one by one.
Uh maybe we'll start with uh
bill of materials.
Let's close our setup
and do a navigation the old way.
Production design, production bill of
material, and let's find our uh standard
bill of material.
So, it got one new field
in the lines.
Here. Component supply method.
So, what I'm trying to do here, I
decided to use these three
components
in my subcontracting operation.
And I plan to deal with them in a
different way.
What do I mean?
I can, from logistic perspective,
have them in my warehouse. Maybe I buy
them in bulk, maybe I produce them
locally. For any reason, they are in my
warehouse.
And I plan to transfer them to vendor
using transfer order.
So, I can uh
tell about that. So, housing airport
will be transferred.
Reservoir assembly,
contrary, I will not be transferring it.
I will
get it on vendor location, like the
place where subcontracting will be
happening, differently. Maybe we'll just
buy it there. Yeah?
So,
I will call it consignment at vendor.
So, I will avoid extra transfer from my
location to vendor location. I will just
place my uh
order for raw materials and ensure that
they will be delivered not to my
location, but to vendor location and
used in the production process.
And the last one, it's a special item. I
cannot buy it for my warehouse, I cannot
buy it for vendor warehouse for very
good reason.
Probably because
it's exactly the same vendor who is
producing the the whole thing. They will
get it for me somehow. Maybe they have a
good deal with a different vendor and
they can buy directly stuff from them,
or maybe they are producing this
component themselves. So, I'm not doing
anything with it.
I will specify that it's vendor
supplied. I will get it from this
vendor.
And then, this component also needs to
be consumed
and included into the cost of a produced
finished good. In this case, it is
airport.
All right, what do we do next? We
certifying this bill of material.
And we could look at
routing, but we will do it at later
stage.
Let's jump directly to the
released
production orders.
And create a new one.
For this item, some quantity. I think
five will be enough.
And our favorite default
main location. Refresh production order.
And we got a line which are we going to
produce calculated. Yeah, I'm using the
uh subcontracting routing here. I
already modified my item.
So,
what else do you want to look at?
Let's start by looking at components.
There are plenty of components, but we
are interested in the first three
because
we are using them in subcontracting. So,
they are linked to subcontracting
operation. We will see it separately.
And you can see location code is
different. Why?
So,
right now, when I created my production
order,
I created demand because I'm going to
consume
these components from these places at
this point of time. So, I need to get
them restocked. Yeah.
So, transfer to vendor. Yeah. I will
buying to my main location and later I
will transfer.
These two already pointing to the
location specified in the vendor card.
Yeah, so like the on vendor card, we
have a new field where we will track
components which are on vendor location.
They still ours, but uh
on different place. So, you can see
consignment and vendor and vendor
supplied.
All right.
Next, jump to the routings.
And here we can see interesting things.
We can see a new fact box which is
providing additional details about
subcontracting.
Which line is a subcontracting? In this
case, it will be the first operation and
you can see it says subcontracting, yes.
And I get some extra details.
You can see that to this line, because
it has a routing link code somewhere
here,
three components are connected. And
everything else is basically zero
because I did nothing.
What do I do? In the old days, I can go
to a subcontracting worksheet and do it
create a
subcontracting order, but not Mhm. It's
still possible today if I'm doing the
bulk operations and there are extra
capabilities there,
but
for simplicity, I can also do it right
from production order routing. I can
just click create subcontracting order.
Purchase order subcontracting purchase
order is created and I can actually open
it and check it. Let's explore.
First of all, vendor name is called bulk
assembly nowadays because we modified
our demo data to include two
subcontractors and they are both linked
to work centers. So, we have two
separate work centers plus two locations
for subcontractors. That should make
demonstration easier and require less
settings. But let's look into the
document itself because it is
unexpectedly
has a lot of lines.
Where are they all coming from? Let's
check line by line and figure it out.
Line number one, this one, is actually
component, the one which we marked in
the as vendor supplied in the bill of
material. So, we are buying it from
exactly this vendor. Yeah.
Okay, first mystery is solved and we are
buying it to the subcontractor location
where it will be consumed
later.
The next lines are all about work which
subcontractor has to perform.
The item line is actually the
routing operation which needs to be
performed.
The line above says airport. It's a
description copied from the production
order line and usually it represents the
name of the finished good.
Why do we insert it here? We have a
setting for this one.
For this behavior.
Let's go to manufacturing setup.
Scroll down to the subcontracting fast
tab and you can see the first toggle
create production order info line, which
is on. And this one instruct system once
subcontracting order is created to
additionally insert comment line with
information about the
product order line description.
Uh maybe it's a good time to look at the
next field, subcontracting component
transfer lead time, which says one day.
We will use it in a later stage.
But before we do that,
we will take a look at the next three
lines. All of them are type of comment
and it looks like they are
instructing or instructions for
subcontractor about what exactly to do
that. So body assembly is a pretty short
description, so we have extra ability to
to put a more text.
Assemble housings, perform visual
inspection,
refer to attachment documentation. Oh,
it's interesting. It's actually not for
myself, so I will remember to
demonstrate you something.
What do you see?
Right now you see nothing because
attachments are empty. But these
attachments
for document header.
One purchase order, if it's created from
subcontracting worksheet, can have a
task related to multiple production
orders or maybe different production
order lines. And definitely they will
have a different instructions.
All right. So, attachment is probably
somewhere else.
Well, let's select this operation
and go to line
attachments.
So, yes, we have information about
attachments per line and we here can see
subcontracting description copied from
some unknown source. And let's explore
where it's coming from all of this. I
will switch from attachment to details
and scroll down to the
subcontracting details fact box, which
has information about connected
production order, so I can easily jump
to my production order to explore,
transfer orders, which are not present
yet, and then
production routings, production
components. Let's open production order.
I'm from here to the routing.
So, first of all, this line uh
which representing
subcontracting operations, we can choose
operations and we will see something new
here.
Subcontracting comment.
And if I will choose, I can see exact
text which was present in the in the
purchase order. So, I can modify it as I
wish and it will be copied next time. I
have access to it also from the
production order routing lines.
Or it can be also inherited from the
standard
uh standard tasks.
We can also see attachments here. And if
I will choose
show details for attachments, you can
see that I have two toggles enabled,
flow to production order and flow to
purchase.
So,
from routing to the purchase document.
That's why this subcontracting
description document was
copied to the subcontracting purchase
order.
What else should we look here at?
Let's go to the very very right and we
can see transfer VIP item.
Work in progress item.
So,
yeah, maybe not very good for the first
operation, but if subcontracting is like
the second one,
then we are probably giving to
subcontractor
not only raw materials. We're giving
them something
not finished. Something which is work in
progress. So, it's not our
airport because it's far far away from
it, but it's also not a collection of
raw materials. It's already
VIP item. How would we call it?
Let's call it like
this way. Coffee machine frame and
housing.
Where do we use it?
And we will use it in transfers.
Let's close routing,
production order, and finally create
transfer.
Actions.
Functions.
Subcontracting.
I believe you can personalize it if you
do a lot of subcontractings. Create
transfer order to subcontractor.
All right. Transfer order is created
from main location to subcontractor
location
and it has two lines. First of all,
component which we decided to move from
our main location to subcontractor
location. Remember that in the
production bill of material, we had a
three different
ways how to
ensure that
components will be available for
subcontractor. And one of them we
decided to be to to transfer from our
location. So, that's a simple one. The
next line is marked as a
transfer VIP item and has absolutely the
same description as I
uh showed before in the
in the routing.
So, once I will post it,
the first line will indeed create item
ledger entries.
The second one, no. No, it will be
registered in a new
ledger entry called work in progress
ledger entry.
Should we try to post it? Yeah, sure.
All right.
And let's maybe scroll to fact box.
Or, we actually have a
line items production with a basically
the same information as we see here.
And let's click on production order
routing because we want to explore
subcontracting details fact box. Here
you can see WIP quantity at
subcontractor quantity five. And we can
drill down and see our ledger entries.
That's actually give us a base if we
will decide to transfer something back.
Yeah, so we know how many we need to
transfer back from subcontractor.
Okay.
Back to purchase document and let's
just post it.
Post, receive.
Should be good.
Okay, I received the component. I
received the
operation.
Uh what else do I want to do?
I can explore my fact box like nothing
is invoiced.
But what if I want to do something
different?
I will go to purchase invoices.
And I already created it to
to to have purchase invoice from some uh
Yeah.
Should be random
a random vendor. And then item charges.
Yes, I'm bank item charges. Should be
any vendor in reality.
And I'm using the large amount.
Uh so, it will be more noticeable. What
do I do next? I will use a line related
information item charge assignment
because I want to allocate this item
charges to
recently posted
purchase uh
purchase receipt. So, let's get receipt
lines.
Scroll, scroll, scroll.
And you can see I have two lines. One of
them component and the second one is
operation body assembly. You can even
see production order connected to it.
Used to be a not possible to select, but
now you can do that.
Allocate everything available. Close.
Post.
We don't want purchase invoice. We want
to go back to production order. So,
nothing happened here on routing line,
but if you go back to release production
order and explore statistics,
you can see
actual cost is right on the
subcontractor cost.
Is only my item charges because I didn't
post invoice for the
uh from the vendor originally.
All right. That's a basic demo. What we
learned? Different logistic uh options.
How to move raw materials differently.
How to move work in progress items with
a transfer orders. How to navigate
between purchase, transfer, and uh
production orders using fact box and
actions available. How to use item
charges to increase cost
for any good reason. Maybe there is a
insurance, logistics, or whatever
allocated to this operation.
Is it it?
Absolutely not. I have more demos for
you.
Let's start with a simple one.
I have
guess amount price demo.
So, in this demo, I'm producing
absolutely the same item. It's a clone
of airport. It has a different item
number, but I didn't change the name.
Same item, same routing, same location.
Different quantity. Quantity 2, 22 in
222.
Let's go to routing
and open
purchase order.
All of them are in the same purchase
order.
For the very good reason, yeah, you can
see a lot of uh valuable comments, but
what we are interested in
we're interested in these lines.
And we'll scroll to the right, and we
can see quantity 2, 22, and 222.
And prices.
And prices are different. So, we have a
pricing mechanism which allows you to
dictate different prices. Let's explore.
Let's navigate to our
item and see prices defined for it.
All right, I choose uh
actions, purchase prices, and
subcontractor prices.
All right. We can see that we defined
three different prices for the same
item.
No different criterias, like the same
work center, same vendor, no standard
tasks. By the way, we are now including
in Dynamics 365 uh standard task codes,
so it will be easy for you to
demonstrate different pricing.
Why I'm not using it here? Hmm.
All right, same item, same date, and
different quantity. Yeah, so zero means
no restrictions, 20 plus or 200 plus.
And prices are different. Okay, 20 plus
and I get 23. That's correct. That's
like the only number which match to our
purchase document. Yeah, logically. 200
use 26. That's interesting. It's not how
pricing in purchase
works, because in
normally, we prefer to give best price.
Yeah, select the the smallest price. In
subcontracting we give
closest match price.
So, even if you are buying 200, it
sounds you should not buy 200. It sounds
you need to place 10 orders by 20 and
then you will
get it cheaper. But apparently our
vendor say like if you place a large
order, you pay more.
Okay, go find another vendor if you if
you can
for smaller sizes. So, it's a first
difference with the pricing engine. So,
prices are more
closest ones. Same goes to dates,
tasks,
unit of measure,
and variants which are not visible right
now.
But why did we see the price 50? Because
you can see it's a 25, 23, and 26. Like
never mentioned 50. That's a different
story. Because our vendor subcontractor
wants minimum amount per deal. So, like
whatever you order, not less than 100
per line.
And we are only producing two items. So,
2 by 25 it's only 50. Yeah? So, system
does it differently.
If
it's less than 100,
put amount as 100 divided by quantity
and this is your price. So, yeah. We
took minimum amount 100 divided by two
and 50 is our price. Let's review.
Exactly the story. So,
quantity is 50 and the total will be
100. So, minimum rule is uh
correct. 23 close match closest match 26
again closest match because 222 is
closer to 200 than 20.
All right, now we understand how pricing
works.
Is it it?
Absolutely no. I have more
demonstrations for you. Let's talk about
warehouse handling. I have couple of
production orders configured for
different warehouses. Let's start with a
simple one, simple one, directed
put-away and white location. I will just
jump to my lines, routings
and create subcontracting order.
This is my subcontracting order and now
I cannot post my receipt
because
it requires warehouse handling. So,
instead, what can I do? Create warehouse
receipt, as expected.
So, now I can create warehouse receipt
and moreover, I can actually go here and
uh
add item trackings. So, I'm not
receiving any random uh item, I'm
receiving item with a serial and uh
tracking.
All right, let's give it some uh
serial numbers
and post receipt.
I can only assign serial numbers and get
put-away created if it is the last
operation. If it's not the last
operation,
then I just use the warehouse receipt
to register a production uh fact of
production. By the way, meanwhile, uh
output was already posted. So, we can go
back to our production
order
and see that
finished quantity has increased. So, I
can actually go navigate to ledger
entries and see
the related order
item ledger entries.
I got three outputs with the serial
numbers
and capacity ledger entries as well.
All right, that's not something like
very, very new because we already had it
in minor release 28.3. What is very new
is
this one.
So, here I'm using location which I
created and called basic. What it does,
it requires put away and pick.
Yeah, no warehouse receipt, no
shipments.
I can use it.
Let's go to lines,
routings,
and do the same.
Create subcontracting order.
Oh,
apparently I already had it created
during the preparation. Do I want to see
it? Yes, I will do. By the way, the
information is right here.
That's very convenient. Okay, show
document.
I have my subcontracting order. Here I
will be creating inventory put away.
Got it.
Warehouse.
Put away lines.
The same story. I can assign serial
numbers here.
I wish we have a this convenient
function here as well, so it will be
Okay, and auto fill quantity to handle.
Done.
I can post it.
I can define serial numbers now on
different level. I can define it in the
production order and then they will be
copied to
uh purchase order. I can define them in
purchase document as well, and then they
will populate inventory put away. So,
up to you or up to your process, when do
you want to define serial numbers. But,
the fact is you can do it on any level
and you can use any receiving method you
like, either normal purchase document,
warehouse receipt, or inventory put
away.
Done. Let's take a look at the list of
uh demos and make sure I didn't miss
anything. And apparently I did not. So,
we definitely saw logistic flows,
raw materials,
work in progress, warehouse handling,
warehouse receipt,
inventory put away
with a
transfer with a serial numbers to I
don't know lot number lot numbers which
we didn't see but you know it works the
same.
Uh
price
cost
>> [snorts]
>> very solid
improvement to our subcontracting model.
Thank you for watching.